# LORENZO NTIBARIKURE

# **Engineering Systems | Physical Modeling | Customer Focus**

ntilau.github.io

in ntilau

ntilau

Findhoven, Netherlands

# **SUMMARY**

My experiences, with a focus on numerical methods, encompass electronic and mechatronic system development and technical sales & support across several industries (Energy & Aerospace, Electronic Design Automation, and Semiconductors).

Leveraging such a background, I am currently helping designers to develop more effectively towards system-level compliance.

### **EXPERIENCE**

#### Sr Engineer - Design Enablement

#### **NXP Semiconductors**

🗂 03/2022 - Present

Eindhoven, Netherlands

- Implemented electromagnetic simulation flows for SoCs development and electromagnetic interference predictions.
- Enhanced vendor solutions to meet the design and integration requirements of the cloud platform.
- Developed problem-resolution automation scripts and applied AI/ML algorithms for electromagnetic surrogate models.

# **Technical Account Manager**

#### **Ansys**

- Utrecht, Netherlands
- Drove customer satisfaction by providing multi-disciplinary technical support and managing global presales activities involving the whole Ansys portfolio & ecosystem.
- Led teams to architect flows across disciplines, focusing on requirements and critical success factors.
- Advised global sales and account engineers on addressable initiatives and pipelines with preliminary requirements and solutions visions.

#### Sr. Applications Engineer

# **Ansys**

- Utrecht, Netherlands
- Executed presales activities for electronic systems across industries, supporting highfrequency solutions and EMC flows across EMEA.
- · Led technical alignment with customers on automotive electrification and connectivity projects, successfully delivering consulting services and trainings.

#### Lead Engineer - Testing

# **Baker Hughes**

**□** 06/2013 - 12/2018

- ▼ Florence, Italy
- Led the development of industrial, ATEX compliant, distributed data acquisition systems to streamline tests execution timelines from months to weeks.
- Resolved 5+ electromagnetic interference issues in NPI validations and factory acceptance tests, contributing to best practices.
- Received an innovation award for patent disclosure of the Structural Vibration Monitoring System and multiple rewards for innovative solutions and customer impact.

# Startup Co-founder

# Università degli Studi di Firenze

**Ö** 06/2012 − 06/2013

Florence, Italy

• Initiated a spin-off, ElectroSoft, to provide efficient numerical codes for design problems.

#### **EDUCATION**

Doctor of Philosophy - PhD, Electronics Engineering

#### Università degli Studi di Firenze

School of "RF, Microwaves and Electromagnetics". Computational Methods focus. With grant (Jan 2011 - Jun 2013).

# Master's Degree, Electronics Engineering

#### Università degli Studi di Firenze

Erasmus Placement/LLP framework thesis semester at Lehrstuhl für Theoretische Elektrotechnik, Universität des Saarlandes. With grant (Sep 2009 - Mar 2010).

# Bachelor's degree, Electrical and Electronics Engineering

Università degli Studi di Firenze

☐ 01/2003 - 04/2008 Florence, Italy

#### **AWARDS**



EMEA TAM of the Year | Ansys (01/2021)

Award for customer and industry focus

# Learn and adapt to win | BHGE (07/2018)

Patent impact award for the disclosure of "Module with sensors arrangement"

# Customers determine our success | BHGE (03/2017)

Bronze award for the GE Aviation's Catalyst FETT advanced test instrumentation consulting

# Customers determine our success | GE (10/2016)

Bronze award for the successful execution of the vibration monitoring system **ZADCO** customer structural vibrations acceptance tests

# Learn and adapt to win | GE (03/2016) Bronze award for the co-generation plant cost savings on the SNC1-2 steam turbine performance validation

Learn and adapt to win | GE (10/2015) Bronze award for the introduction and validation of an effective, cost-saving, structural vibrations digital integration algorithm aimed at accurately deriving speed & displacements measurements from ATEX-compliant accelerometers

External focus | GE (06/2014) • Led team promotion and value proposition pitches to business angels. Bronze award for the RCA activities on • Developed first opportunities in the defense industry. Cessao Onerosa, ADRE monitoring system EMI noise mitigation and customer assurance **Doctoral Researcher** Università degli Studi di Firenze Giorgio Barzilai Prize | SIEm (09/2012) **□** 01/2011 - 06/2013 Florence, Italy Best paper award for young researchers, for the work "Model order reduction in • Researched applied & computational electromagnetics, presenting 10+ papers, advis-Finite Element analysis of phased array ing student theses, and supporting examinations. antennas" presented at the XIX RiNEm Developed a high-frequency electromagnetic 3D finite element C++ code for domain decomposition and nonlinear formulations. Ph.D. studies grant | UniFi (12/2010) Architected a methodology using MathWorks Simulink and Ansys HFSS for electro-Full tuition fees and allowance for remagnetic compatibility in variable speed drive systems. search on Electromagnetic Compatibility modeling techniques in variable speed drive systems - with GE/Nuovo Pignone Visiting Researcher Universität des Saarlandes Dean's listing | UniFi (04/2010) **1**0/2009 - 02/2010 Commissione di Laurea Specialistica in In- Saarbrücken, Germany gegneria Elettronica presieduta dal Prof. • Developed model order reduction in finite element analysis of antenna arrays for fast Piero Tortoli (Prot. 1051 n. class. III/9.1.2 and accurate beamforming. del 24 Maggio 2010) • Implemented Matlab code for a 3000x matrix reduction and 300x speedup in antenna pattern computation LLP/Erasmus Placement grant | UniFI (10/2009)Thesis work semester relocation support **R&D** Engineer at Universität des Saarlandes Università degli Studi di Firenze **1**2/2007 - 03/2008 Florence, Italy CERTIFICATION • Developed wireless connectivity for a battery-powered avalanche rescue ground pen-Professional Engineer, etrating radar, optimizing firmware for fast full-duplex/half-duplex conversion timing. ID:ES2010277049000038 • Executed the design and assembly of an ISM 868 MHz serial modem PCB prototype Università degli Studi di Firenze with off-the-shelf MCU and Radio (sub-GHz RFFE). Achieved successful wireless system resulting in improved signal detection accuracy. **COURSES PROJECTS** Command of the Message Bearings loading test rig **Ansys** □ 06/2020 Remote Baker Hughes, a GE Company **Ö** 05/2018 - 12/2018 Florence, Italy JAWS: Just Another Way of Selling Conceptual design of a novel bearings loading test rig aimed at validating bearings **Ansvs**  □ 02/2020 Paris, France • Investigated on modeling methods of EM coupling between power (variable speed drive system) and signals cabling systems to predict potential interference issues. GE Crotonville: Delivering Customer Im-**GE** Aviation's Catalyst GE Oil & Gas Baker Hughes, a GE Company □ 03/2016 Munich, Germany Prague, Czech Republic Total Quality Lean Six Sigma Green Belt • Led special instrumentation design and global technical reviews of FETT with design **GE Oil & Gas** and testing teams (Czech Rep., Poland, USA, Canada). □ 06/2014 • Contributed to >4 M\$ corss-P&L project and customer satisfaction. Florence, Italy

#### Gas Turbine embedded SAW sensors

Baker Hughes, a GE Company

**Ö** 02/2018 - 12/2018

Florence, Italy

• Collaborated with University of Florence to investigate the high-frequency numerical modeling of SAW sensors for the accuracy control of temperature measurements.

LM9000: 65 MW aeroderivative gas turbine

Baker Hughes, a GE Company

**Ö** 06/2018 - 12/2018

Florence, Italy

# **LANGUAGES**

Semiconductors

**SKILLS** 

Testing

Engineering

Sales

**Customer Satisfaction** 

Finite Element Analysis

Python

**Simulations** 

Strategy

Scripting

RF

Management

Leadership

Matlab

Electronics

 Contributed to conceptual instrumentation design and test rigs erection, data acquisition architecture and control system design by technical and HAZOP reviews. Dutch Cross'd **English Ö** 01/2018 - 11/2018 Florence, Italy French • Social networking app PoC based on Bluetooth Low Energy ranging. PoC with Apache Cordova and an AWS EC2 instance German **BLE Asset Tracking** Italian **Ö** 07/2017 - 09/2017 Florence, Italy Sub 5\$/Unit PoC of BLE tags (TI's CC2640) with firmware optimized for long-battery Kirundi life, aimed at asset tracking and inventory management Spanish GE Power slip-ring digital telemetry Baker Hughes, a GE Company **PUBLICATIONS** 

**Ö** 04/2017 - 05/2017

Florence, Italy

- Ran Ansys HFSS simulations to optimize signal integrity over slip-ring connections (power supply and ethernet transmission lines)
- · Achieved shrinking of the rings spacing leading to manufacturing costs reduction
- 4 weeks-FTE cross-P&L billing and customer satisfaction

# Wet gas compressors at KLAB

#### **GE Oil & Gas**

Haugesund, Norway

- Designed and procured validation equipment for ATEX zone 1 test bench.
- Developed Ex-d antenna and low noise amplifier system for GPS synchronization on NI's PXI systems.
- Managed IEC 60079-11 simple apparatus compliance on load cells upon using extremely low voltage (1.5 V) Ex-ia Wheatstone bridge conditioners.

#### Power density compressor

#### **GE Oil & Gas**

**Ö** 03/2014 - 05/2016

Florence, Italy

- Led the commissioning Fieldbus Foundation use in testing lab for more than 240 pressure transducers (0.1% uncertainty) upon identifing the proper Firmware configuration which enabled for massive and accurate pressure measurements.
- Managed capacitive vibration probes ATEX-compliance.
- Developed electrostatic numerical model to predict capacitance variation in various surroundings and target shape conditions.
- Contributed to DM37/08 compliance of the test rig contract specification, including power and signaling cabling selection and proper installation.

# SNC1-2 steam turbine performance evaluation in 6.2 MW cogeneration plant **GE Oil & Gas**

**Ö** 09/2015 - 04/2016

Florence, Italy

- Defined novel pressure hookups method at lower cost and better performance to achieve accuracy controlled inter-stage enthalpy measurements according to ASME PTC 19.11.
- Programmed a CAN to Modbus TCP embedded module to enable static torque measurements on a MagCanica telemetry.

# GE-6G PowerGen Module Structural Vibrations Monitoring System

**GE Oil & Gas** 

**11/2015 - 03/2016** 

Massa, Italy

# Patents

• L. Ntibarikure, "Module with sensors arrangement," US20180180464A1, 2018. [Online]. Available: https://patents.google. com/patent/US20180180464A1/en.

# Books

· L. Ntibarikure, Contributions to the Art of Finite Elements in Electromagnetics. Florence, Italy, 2014. [Online]. Available: https://hdl. handle.net/2158/843133.

# Journal Articles

- L. Ntibarikure, "Multiphysics simulations for 5g rfics and socs," Bits&Chips, 2019.
- F. Barone, A. Signorini, L. Ntibarikure, T. Fiore, F. Di Pasquale, and C. J. Oton, "Fiberoptic liquid level sensing by temperature profiling with an fbg array," Sensors, vol. 18, no. 8, 2018. [Online]. Available: https:// www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/18/8/2422.
- L. Ntibarikure, G. Pelosi, and S. S. and, "Harmonic balance domain decomposition finite elements for nonlinear passive microwave devices analysis," Electromagnetics, vol. 34, no. 3-4, pp. 239-252, 2014. DOI: 10.1080/02726343.2014.877756.
- L. Ntibarikure, G. Pelosi, and S. Selleri, "Efficient harmonic balance analysis of waveguide devices with nonlinear dielectrics," **IEEE Microwave and Wireless Components** Letters, vol. 22, no. 5, pp. 221-223, 2012. DOI: 10.1109/LMWC.2012.2192420.

## Conference Proceedings

• L. Ntibarikure, G. Pelosi, and S. Selleri, "Assessment of the performances of gmres(r) using a domain decomposition approach as a preconditioner," in Proceedings, XX Riunione Nazionale di Elettromagnetismo (XX RiNEm), Padua, Italy, 2014. [Online]. Available: https: //inspirehep.net/literature/1403858.

- Developped ATEX-compliant distributed acquisition system for more than 150 vibration measurement points, with 40 kHz analog bandwidth, WiFi5 backhaul to storage and real-time monitoring, with GPS or daisy-chain clock distribution synchronization
- Hands-on design of 3D assemblies and BOM for timely delivery and cost optimization of certified equipment in less than 4 months (vs typ. 8 months).
- Introduced and consolidated with third party metrology a software based velocity and displacement real-time computation from accelerometers, achieving direct \$150k savings, and subsequent lab processes OPEX benefits.
- Customer value delivered as onsite Turbomachinery Modules structural commissioning with patented solution

NovaLT16 gas turbine, bearings and cooling component tests

#### **GE Oil & Gas**

**Ö** 04/2014 - 10/2015

♥ Florence, Italy

- Design and validation of smartbox (field datalogger) for analog signals.
- Defined EMC-aware measurement loops design to achieve noise immunity and enhanced measurement accuracies, rigorously applying EN 61000 guidelines (CENELEC 25).

GE Aviation's GE9X High Pressure Compressor

#### GE Oil & Gas

**Ö** 01/2014 - 04/2014

Massa, Italy

- High density data acquisition system design for GE Aviation's compressor test in Massa.
- Performed mitigation on EMC noise due to 130 kW variable speed ventilation system

BCL306 and BCL317 centrifugal compressors rotordynamics

#### **GE Oil & Gas**

□ 06/2013 - 03/2014

▼ Florence, Italy

 Performed an Ex-p execution of stability's magnetic exciter, contributed to the resolution of customer's opened nonconformity on rotordynamic vibrations upon conducting an electromagnetic interference on Bently Nevada's 3500 RCA.

Finite Elements Software (FES)

### Università degli Studi di Firenze

□ 06/2011 - 02/2014

▼ Florence, Italy

 FES is an open source C++ framework for the development of "ad-hoc" simulation software aimed at a rapid implementation of novel numerical methods based on the Galerkin method. Core formulations validated reusing meshes from commercial packages (Comsol, HFSS)

Phased array antennas model order reduction

#### Universität des Saarlandes

**1**0/2009 - 02/2010

Saarbrücken, Germany

- Developed in Matlab efficient near-to-far-fields formulations for fast electromagnetic radiation computation in large finite elements problems exploiting model order reduction with spectral interpolation for beam steering and pattern angles
- Modeled a large patch antenna array, assessing accuracy and performances through mesh/model export from Ansoft HFSS v11

RS-232 modem in ISM 868 MHz band

#### **University of Florence**

- ▼ Florence, Italy
- Designed and prototyped an 868 MHz wireless link for a ground penetration radar remote control over RS-232 protocol
- C-coded the PIC microcontroller FW and optimized in Assembly to garantee the fullduplex operation over half-duplex TI's CC1100 radio.
- Evaluated the performance of the wireless link in open field

- L. Ntibarikure, "Model order reduction in finite elements analysis of phased array antennas," in *Proceedings, XIX Riunione Nazionale* di Elettromagnetismo (XIX RiNEm), S. d. E. SiEm, Ed., Roma, Italy, 2012.
- L. Ntibarikure, G. Pelosi, and S. Selleri, "Harmonic balance finite element analysis of third order intermodulation products in ferrite devices," in *Proceedings, XIX Riunione Nazionale di Elettromagnetismo (XIX RiNEm)*, S. d. E. SiEm, Ed., Roma, Italy, 2012.